<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Eternity, or, The weightiness of the unseen concerns of the other world, from their duration opened, proved, and applyed in a sermon preached in Worcestershire / by Tho. Badland ...</title>
            <author>Badland, Tho. (Thomas)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1676</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 86 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 40 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A28922</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B390</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R37054</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">16197765</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 16197765</idno>
            <idno type="VID">105047</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A28922)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 105047)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1085:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Eternity, or, The weightiness of the unseen concerns of the other world, from their duration opened, proved, and applyed in a sermon preached in Worcestershire / by Tho. Badland ...</title>
                  <author>Badland, Tho. (Thomas)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 75 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Sampson Evans, book-seller in Worcester, and are to be sold by N. Simmons ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1676.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Corinthians, 2nd, IV, 18 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Future life --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:105047:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:105047:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>ETERNITY: OR, THE WEIGHTINESS OF THE UNSEEN CONCERNS Of the other World, from their Duration: Opened, proved, and applyed in a Sermon preached in WORCESTER-SHIRE.</p>
            <p>By <hi>THO. BADLAND,</hi> Miniſter of the Goſpel.</p>
            <q>
               <p>Illi brevi huic vitae ſe totos implicent, qui aeterna neſciunt.</p>
               <bibl>Hieron.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Sampſon Evans,</hi> Book-ſeller in <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſter,</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>N. Simmons</hi> at the Prince's Arms in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church Yard, 1676.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:105047:2"/>
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Jan. 18. 1675.</date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>IMprimatur haec Concio de Aeternitate</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Gul. Jane</hi> S. T. B. Rev. in Chriſto Patri D<hi rend="sup">no</hi> 
                  <hi>Henrico</hi> Epiſc. <hi>Londin.</hi> agrave; Sac Domeſt.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:105047:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Chriſtian Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THis Sermon was never intended to peep out of the bounds of a popular auditory: The importunity of Friends, who would not otherwiſe be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied, hath brought it upon the publick Stage. The Diſcourſe is but ſhort and mean for ſo large and ponderous a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject; but the ſmalneſs of the Volume may bring it to more hands, and the plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs thereof is moſt apt and congruous
<pb facs="tcp:105047:3"/> for their uſe and benefit, for whom 'tis chiefly ſent abroad. The poor and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned, which are alwaies moſt numerous, and who are alſo no leſs concerned in the weighty affair of Eternity than others, cannot reach nor perhaps ſo well under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the bigger and more learned, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe more uſeful Treatiſes of this ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject that are written: And to ſuch, I hope, the <hi>Father of Mercies</hi> at leaſt will make this haſty ſcrible a Bleſſing; which is the great deſire, and ſhall be the ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt prayer of the Author, who is</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thine in <hi>Chriſt</hi> T. B.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:105047:3"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>2 Cor. 4.18. the latter part.</bibl>
                  <p>But the things which are not ſeen are eternal.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <div type="introduction">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O paſs by the <hi>Analyſis</hi> of this Chapter; toward the latter end you have the Apoſtle ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainting us with the reaſon of his own, and other Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles and Miniſters of the Goſpel's conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, boldneſs, unwearied diligence, and faithfulneſs in the work of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> in the midſt of the great perils, diſtreſſes and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zards attending them in their courſe. The main of their encouragement is this, that their utmoſt ſufferings and ſorrows in their duty were their high advantage: They
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:105047:4"/> worked for them <hi>a far more exceeding and eternal weight of glory: verſ.</hi> 17. This prize (he tells us) their hearts were on in the contempt of all things here. This they would not loſe, whatever they loſt, or ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd in purſuance of it. And that they were rational in this reſolution, he evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denceth from the Glory of the prize they had in their eye. This is the moſt excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent prize, and infinitely ſufficient to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence them for all loſſes and afflictions befalling them in the due proſecution of it. There is no compariſon between things that are ſeen, and things that are not ſeen. The inviſible concerns of the other world do as much excell outward and viſible con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns, as Eternity is of more conſequence than time. <hi>The things that are ſeen</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>are temporal;</hi> but <hi>The things that are not ſeen are eternal.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So that the words are a reaſon why the Apoſtles had their hearts ſo fixed on the bleſſings of the unſeen world, as lightly to ſet by the moſt terrible diſcouragements attending them in purſuance of them. They
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:105047:4"/> were <hi>eternal;</hi> whereas their outward af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions and miſeries were but temporal. In the words there is,</p>
               <p n="1">1. The things ſpoken of: <hi>Things which are not ſeen;</hi> that is, the inviſible concerns and enjoyments which yet are out of our view in the other world; The mercies of the Paradiſe of God, and the miſeries of the unquenchable fire, which will be the portion of the damned. The happy eſtate of the Bleſſed, and the wretched condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Curſed and condemned beyond the borders of time; Theſe are the things which in general the Apoſtle means by things unſeen.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Here is ſomething affirmed of theſe unſeen things: They are <hi>Eternal;</hi> that is, they are of everlaſting duration; they will never have an end, but continue for ever and for ever. When this world and all Sublunary things are burnt up and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh, and all concerns of time have a pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riod; the happineſs of the Saints, and the miſery of the wicked ſhall laſt and continue: they ſhall never vaniſh or have
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:105047:5"/> a period. The Godly ſhall triumph in God's Love, and the wicked weep and howl under God's fury, to the endleſs bounds of eternity. When the ſpace of million of millions of years, according to our poor and ſhallow reckoning, are over, the happineſs of the Pious, and the ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row and perplexity of the wicked is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the nearer a period: ſtill the Saints joy continues, and ſtill the wickeds ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings continue, and are no nearer end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing than at the beginning; Night and day to eternity the Holy ſhall rejoyce and triumph; and night and day to eternity the impious ſhall have gnaſhing of teeth, and mourn. Unſeen things are eternal.</p>
               <p>From the words thus explained, were raiſed theſe two Doctrines.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>
                     <hi>Doctr.</hi> 1.</label> 
                  <hi>The weighty concerns attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing us in the other world are unſeen.</hi> The entertainment that immortal Souls will meet with, when death comes, and hath done its work upon them, we cannot here behour. We perceive not the triumphant joys of the Glorified here: nor do we per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:105047:5"/> the doleful howlings of the damned here. 'Tis true, we have ſomething of theſe weighty concerns revealed in the Word: but yet they are not within our view. We ſee not now the Saints Crowns or Glorious Robes, and we hear not now their melodious and tranſporting Songs of triumph and praiſe, wherewith they are priviledged in the Kingdom of their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; and we ſee not now the wickeds horrour, torments and inſupportable ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings in the Helliſh Lake: we have only the report of theſe things, though it be an infallible report. And doubtleſs, this is the main cauſe why Heaven is no more prized, and no more vigorouſly purſued; and Hell is no more abhorred, and ſtre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuouſly and diligently avoided and ſhunned by Mortals; they believe not theſe things, becauſe they ſee them not, had they ſeen the happineſs of the Righteous in God's Eternal Kingdom, or the miſery of the impious, in the Infernal priſon; or had they believing apprehenſions of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quivalent to ſenſe; they could not neglect
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:105047:6"/> them, they could not chooſe but look up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, as the Apoſtle here doth, as the moſt weighty affair and concerns.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>
                     <hi>Doctr.</hi> 2.</label> 
                  <hi>The weighty concerns of the unſeen world are eternal.</hi> They are not fading or vaniſhing, but of never ending continuance and duration. The trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phant world's felicity ſhall never have a period, and the damned world's miſery ſhall never expire. When innumerable years are paſt and gone, the Saints triumph is as far from a period, as at the beginning; and the ſorrows and ſufferings of the wicked are no nearer expiring than at the beginning.</p>
               <p>This laſt is the Doctrine we intend to handle; and in the proſecution thereof, we ſhall obſerve this Method.
<list>
                     <item>1. We ſhall prove it.</item>
                     <item>2. We ſhall ſhew what is imply'd in this word <hi>Eternal,</hi> and ſo the weigh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ineſs of <hi>Unſeen</hi> concerns.</item>
                     <item>3. We ſhall make ſome application.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <p>Firſt, we ſhall prove th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Doctrine, <hi>That
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:105047:6"/> the weighty concerns of the unſeen world are eternal.</hi> And that,
<list>
                     <item>1. By Scripture plainly.</item>
                     <item>2. By induction from Scripture and Nature.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <p>1. We ſhall prove the Doctrine by plain Scripture, <hi>Mat.</hi> 25. <hi>ult. Theſe ſhall go away into everlaſting puniſhment, but the Righteous into life eternal.</hi> Here you ſee the rewards of the other world, that all ſhall reap, are ſtyled everlaſting and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal. <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.2. <hi>Many of them that ſleep in the duſt of the Earth ſhall awake, ſome to everlaſting life, and ſome to ſhame and ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting contempt.</hi> Both the reward of the Godly and the impious is here called <hi>Ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting</hi> in the unſeen world. So you have the Scripture ſpeaking of the Righteous and the wicked particularly, and proclaiming their reward to be eternal and everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. Thus 'tis ſaid the Godly ſeek for <hi>Eternal</hi> life in the other world, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.7. and, that <hi>They are heirs of Eternal life, Titus</hi> 3.7. and, that <hi>They have an Houſe not made with hands eternal in the Heavens,</hi>
                     <pb n="8" facs="tcp:105047:7"/> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.1. And the Apoſtle tells us, that he therefore <hi>endured all things for the Elects ſake, that they may alſo obtain the ſalvation, which is in Jeſus Chriſt, with eternal Glory,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.10. ſo, Heaven is called their <hi>Everlaſting Habitation, Luke</hi> 16.9. And as the enjoyments of the Saints are eternal; ſo likewiſe are the miſeries of the wicked. They are to be puniſhed with <hi>Everlaſting deſtruction from the preſence of the Lord, and the Glory of his power,</hi> 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.9. they are to be caſt into <hi>Everlaſting fire, Mat.</hi> 18.8. or into fire that ſhall <hi>never be quenched,</hi> and where <hi>the worm dieth not, Mark</hi> 9.44. So alſo 'tis ſaid, that <hi>they ſhall be tormented day and night for ever, and for ever, Rev.</hi> 20.10.15.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <p>2. We ſhall prove the Doctrine by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction from Scripture and Nature.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. The Soul is eternal and dies not, and therefore muſt be happy or miſerable for ever. This cannot be killed, <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.28. when it leaveth the Body, it doth not ſleep or die as the Body doth, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 12.7. and when 'tis again re-united to the Body
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:105047:7"/> at the Reſurrection, 'twill never be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated from it; but Body and Soul are joyned together at the Reſurrection for Everlaſting life, or Everlaſting ſhame and contempt, <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.2. and therefore they will have an Eternal Exiſtence. At the Reſurrection the very Body it ſelf will be raiſed incorruptible; <hi>Our corru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption muſt put on incorruption,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.53. Though at preſent our Bodies die and moul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to duſt, yet at the Reſurrection they will not be capable of corruption. We ſhall then die no more a Natural death, <hi>Luke</hi> 20.36. And if Body and Soul will live eternally after the Reſurrection-day, they muſt needs be either happy or mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable to eternity; if they have for ever an Exiſtence, they muſt needs have a felicitous or infelicitous Exiſtence. If they do not vaniſh into nothing, or are not corrupted, killed, or ſeparated; then they will certainly for ever groan or triumph, rejoyce or mourn.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Eternal rewards are promiſed, or threatned: God doth not promiſe to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnify
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:105047:8"/> mercy and loving kindneſs to the Saints for a ſmall ſeaſon only, but to E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity; nor doth he threaten momentany loſſes or ſufferings only to the wicked and impious, but everlaſting. <hi>The Righteous ſhall ſhine as the Stars for ever and ever, Dan.</hi> 12.3. And the wicked have <hi>dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> for ever reſerved for them, 2 <hi>Peter</hi> 2.17. <hi>Believers</hi> ſhall never periſh or die, <hi>John</hi> 11.26. And the <hi>Impenitent</hi> are to be caſt into fire that ſhall never be quench<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>Mark</hi> 9.43. This is the encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that God doth give his People, they ſhall have everlaſting joy upon their heads ere long: and this is the diſcouragement he gives the wicked, they ſhall be puniſhed with eternal deſtruction, or tormented day and night for ever and for ever. Oh! <hi>Heaven</hi> will have Believers triumphing in it to the utmoſt limits and bounds of Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity; for God hath promiſed it to them. And <hi>Hell</hi> will have ungodly Souls and the finally impenitent, weeping and gnaſhing their teeth in it for ever more: for God hath fore-told and threatned it; and he is
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:105047:8"/> a true, juſt, and Righteous GOD.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. GOD, that is engaged to diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute theſe Rewards, is eternal; he liveth for ever to ſee the execution of what ever hath gone out of his mouth. As he was from everlaſting, ſo he will continue to everlaſting. He <hi>inhabits eternity, Iſa.</hi> 57.15. The <hi>Eternal God</hi> is the refuge, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort and ſalvation of the Saints, <hi>Deut.</hi> 33.27. And the confuſion, diſcomfort and and terrour of the impious and wicked. If <hi>Jehovah</hi> himſelf could die, the Saints happineſs would expire, and have a pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riod; and the wickeds and damneds mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery in Hell would be over: but he living, who hath promiſed and threatned, and is engaged to accompliſh the Saints hopes, and wicked's fears; we may be ſure they will laſt for ever. Oh! God hath no end of daies, <hi>Jehovah</hi>'s age will never expire. He is Eternal that hath undertaken to priviledg the Pious with eternal Life, and reward the Impious with eternal Death; therefore unſeen concerns will be eternal.</p>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:105047:9"/>
                  <p n="4">4. As God is eternal, ſo he will be eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally Alſufficient to make good his word. As he was Almighty, and Infinite, and boundleſs in all perfections from eternity; ſo he will remain unto eternity. From <hi>everlaſting to everlaſting he is God, Pſ.</hi> 90.2. He will never deſcend from the Throne, or become frail, or unable to execute his promiſes or threatnings. He is the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal and immortal King, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.17. He is independent for ever, and can perform his pleaſure to all eternity. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his Decree and Law touching the end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs condition of the Righteous and wicked will ſtand. Alas! God can as eaſily make the Righteous immortally happy, and the impious immortally miſerable, as uphold the world and all things therein upon the borders of time. He lives continually in the ſame Majeſty, Glory, and Perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that he is inveſted with to this day: And he will never have his Omnipotency impaired, diminiſhed, or weakned. If God were capable to be dethroned, or to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come infirm or weak for the accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:105047:9"/> of his projects or revealed Will; the ungodly might hope for an expiration of their ſorrows, and the Righteous might fear a period of their Joy and Felicity: but God being unchangeable, and immu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably the ſame to everlaſting; the hopes of the one, and the fears of the other will be vain.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. God will eternally delight in the happineſs of the Saints, and miſeries of the wicked; and therefore both the one and the other will be eternal. Touching the Pious 'tis ſaid, that 'tis the Father's good pleaſure to give them a Kingdom, <hi>Luke</hi> 12.32. They are the Perſons, that <hi>Jehovah</hi> delights to honour: their Glory is God's Glory, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.12. <hi>JESUS CHRIST</hi> will come to be glorified in them at the Reſurrection-day, when he ſhall ſet the Crown of Heavenly Felicity and magnificency upon their heads, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.10. So that their happineſs and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>altation will be God's Glory, Delight and Rejoycing; and therefore will be eternal. 'Twill continue as long as God ſhall
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:105047:10"/> delight in it, and that will be for ever more. So likewiſe the miſery of the wicked in Hell will be to the glory of God's Juſtice and Righteouſneſs; and therefore will be eternal, even as long as God doth continue juſt and righteous, which will be for ever. So alſo God doth rejoyce in their perdition and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction; he laughs at their calamity, and mocks at their diſtreſs, when they are remedileſs, <hi>Prov.</hi> 1.26. And therefore though they call upon him, he will not anſwer them; though they ſeek him early, they ſhall not find him, that is, not mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful or gracious to them. He that made them (ſaith the <hi>Prophet</hi>) will not have mercy on them; and he that formed them, will ſhew them no ſavour, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 27.11. So that you ſee, that both the happineſs of the Godly, and miſery of the wicked in the other world, will be God's delight and his Glory: and therefore they will be eternal.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. The Saints cannot forfeit their hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs, and the wicked cannot purchaſe
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:105047:10"/> or make ſatisfaction for their Redemptio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> from their miſery in the other world<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and therefore both will be eternal. 'Ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> apparent that in Heaven the Saints are as the confirmed Angels, and ſo not capable to be tempted to evill, or to fall from God. Their ſeparated Souls in Eternall Manſions are ſaid to be made perfect, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 12.23. And into God's Paradiſe, which is their glorious Abode and Habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, there entreth nothing that defileth, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.27. Whilſt they are in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of their Father, they are under the fulleſt communications of ſanctifying, and preventing, and triumphing Grace. Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs is their element; duty love and praiſe to God is their very food and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creation; and ſin is as lothſom, as death and the moſt exquiſite miſeries and torments are to us. There alſo they have no tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pter, and nothing to be a bait or allure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to draw them from God: which with the conſideration of their corrobating and confirming Grace doth proclaim, that they cannot ſin, or forfeit the mercies where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:105047:11"/> they are priviledg'd: And therefore they will not loſe their happineſs. God will not deprive them of their mercies without cauſe, he will not ſend them from his Triumphant Kingdom, to which they are Heirs, till they cut off the entail of eternal Bleſſings, and that will be never: So that their happineſs muſt needs be eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal. And then, the wicked will never make ſatisfaction in order to their redemption from Hell; and therefore their miſeries muſt be alſo eternal. They muſt ſtay there, till they have pay'd the utmoſt mite they are endebted unto Divine Juſtice, <hi>Matt.</hi> 5.26. and that will be for ever more: And therefore that expreſſion, <hi>Till thou haſt pay'd the laſt mite, thou ſhalt not depart thence,</hi> ſignifies as much as, Thou ſhalt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver depart thence, <hi>Luke</hi> 12.59. Oh! all the ſufferings of the damned, even to an endleſs eternity will not ſatisfy for their ſin and diſobedience here. And 'tis apparent, they have none elſe to ſatisfy for them; <hi>CHRIST</hi> will die no more for them. There remains no more Sacrifice
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:105047:11"/> for ſin, when the price of <hi>CHRIST</hi>'s Blood is neglected. Oh! the Godly will not loſe their happineſs, and the wicked will never get redemption from Hell; as 'tis in the <hi>Parable,</hi> There is an <hi>Unpaſſable Gulf</hi> between the Glorified and the damned, ſo that they cannot paſs the one to the other, <hi>Luke</hi> 16.26. and therefore their condition in the other world will be eternal.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. If the Saints happineſs were not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal, 'twould much diſcomfort them in the other world; and if the wicked's mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery were not eternal, 'twould much com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort them, and alleviate their miſeries and extremities in the Unſeen world: and therefore both are eternal. The Saints have fulneſs of joy in God's everlaſting Kingdom; and therefore have no expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that 'twill have an end: And the damned have perfection of miſery in the Infernal priſon; and therefore have, no hope that their ſorrows will ever have a period. Reaſon will tell you, that if Triumphant Souls had any apprehenſions
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:105047:12"/> that their felicitous eſtate ſhould at length expire, it would much abate their glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious peace and tranquillity. And Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon will alſo tell you, that, if the wicked had any hopes that their ſorrows and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite torments ſhould at length ceaſe, it would ſomething at leaſt mitigate their infelicity and grief; but this word <hi>Eternal</hi> added to the enjoyments of the Glorified filleth them with perfect Triumph, exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding all penſiveneſs fear and dolour. And the ſame word <hi>Eternal</hi> or <hi>Everlaſting</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to the ſorrows and miſeries of the damned makes them moſt exquiſite, and ſets Hell a roaring moſt diſmally. Oh! that the pleaſures of the Saints are for ever more, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16.11. this makes them pleaſures indeed: And that the anguiſh, perplexity and extremities of the damned are for ever more, this makes them per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly dolefull indeed.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. Nature doth ſeem to evidence this Truth, that things unſeen are eternal. The very <hi>Heathens</hi> are taught to believe in general that the Good ſhall be everlaſtingly
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:105047:12"/> happy, and the wicked everlaſtingly mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable, in the other world. Not only the <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> but the <hi>Mahometans;</hi> yea, and the <hi>Pagans,</hi> that have not unman'd themſelves, do hold that after this life Men and Women ſhall live in a felicitous or dolefull condition for ever. The Soul's immortality is commonly believed, even where <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> is not known: Nature hath dictated this to thoſe that never heard the Scripture-revelation; and if the Soul dies not, it muſt needs be happy or mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable for ever.</p>
                  <p>Now, lay all theſe allegations together, and how apparent and undoubted is this Doctrine, that the weighty concerns of the unſeen world are eternal.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <p>2. We come to ſhew you what is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed in this word <hi>(Eternal)</hi> and ſo the weightineſs of unſeen concerns: And there are three things implied in it.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That the Unſeen concerns of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther world have continuance or are laſting, they are not of ſhort or ſmall duration. Our lives here cannot be ſaid to be eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:105047:13"/> becauſe they are but of ſhort continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance; yea, they are ſaid to flee away as a Weaver's ſhuttle, <hi>Job</hi> 7.6. and are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>par'd to a vapour that ſoon vaniſheth: but now the happineſs of Heaven, and the ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings of Hell are more laſting. They continue not a 100 or a 1000 Years only, but many millions of millions of Years: When many Ages and Generations of Years are paſt and gone, yet ſtill the Saints feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city and the wicked's miſery and ſorrow continueth. When the Saints have been in the Kingdom of their Father triumphing in his love, as long as this World ſhall laſt or endure; yet they have thouſands of Years of the ſame felicity ſtill behind. And when the wicked have been in Hell groan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and hideouſly roaring under the moſt doleful ſufferings, as long as this World doth endure; yet they have millions of Years of the ſame miſery, ſorrow, and ſuffering; ſtill behind. Oh! <hi>Eternity</hi> doth note not a ſhort or tranſitory ſeaſon, but a ſpace <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> continuance beyond the limits of time: an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> verily, this doth beſpeak unſeen things,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:105047:13"/> or the happineſs or miſery of the other World, to be fearfully and dreadfully weighty; eſpecially in compariſon of our concerns here, that are all ſhut up in the narrow compaſs and bounds of a little time. Heaven is the Saints, and Hell is the wickeds long abode and habitation; whereas our ſtay here is comparatively very ſhort. The enjoyments of your other world are continuing, and not of a ſhort, fading, or tranſitory nature.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Eternity</hi> implies continuance alſo without intermiſſion, or any diſcontinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance. 'Tis not like the life of mortals that hath a mixture of joy and ſorrow, or a ſucceſſion of content and diſcontent: but the happineſs of the Saints continues with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any intervening infelicity or ſorrow; And the miſery of the wicked continues in Hell without the intermixture of any joy or comfort whatſoever. Oh! ſo long as Eternity laſts, the Pious will be tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphing in the higheſt Heavens; and ſo long as Eternity laſts, the wicked will have weeping and gnaſhing of teeth in the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fernal
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:105047:14"/> priſon. The Saints ſhall not weep an hour or a moment; they ſhall not grieve or be ſadned the continuance of the twink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of an eye during their abode in the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther World: And the wicked ſhall not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce an hour or a minute, they ſhall have no intermiſſion of their ſorrow or miſery in the other World. The Saints joy will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue or laſt without the leaſt mixture of grief to allay their happineſs; and the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eds grief, perplexity and horror will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue and laſt without the leaſt mixture of joy or comfort to alleviate their infelicity. The <hi>Rich man</hi> in Hell is not allow'd a drop of water to eaſe or refreſh him for a moment's ſeaſon, <hi>Luke</hi> 16.24, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And how much more conſiderable are unſeen concerns in this reſpect than all our concerns here? Alas! who is there here that continues in a conſtant tenure of happineſs or miſery without change, during the daies of their vanity in this World? The moſt felicitous hath ſome ſorrow mixed with his joy here: and the moſt miſerable hath ſome in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tervening hours or minutes of refreſhment
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:105047:14"/> or eaſe here: but in Eternity there is no change at all. The Saints rejoyce ſtill, and are immutably triumphing; and the wicked mourn alwaies, and are unchangeably over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelm'd with diſmal amazement and aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment. The happineſs of the one is eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, and the miſery of the other is eternal, and unchangeably ſo for the leaſt moment.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Eternity</hi> notes continuance without any period, or length of ſpace without any end: and this completes the Saints joy, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects the damneds miſery in the other world. 'Tis not only a laſting continuance, and a continuance without intermiſſion, but 'tis an everlaſting continuance without any final diſcontinuance<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> When the bounds of time, yea ten thouſand millions of millions of the bounds of time are paſſed over and gone; yet the Triumphs of the Glorified, and the roaring and ſorrows of the damned are no nearer ending than at the beginning. <hi>Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity</hi> is a ſpace of continuance immeaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, and inexpreſſible, yea and inconcei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vable 'Tis pictured out by a ring or circle, which you may turn round, but cannot find
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:105047:15"/> any end in it. And though we might give you ſtrange meaſures of <hi>Eternity,</hi> yet we ſhall fall infinitely ſhort of fully meaſuring it: we ſhall only ſet before you one, which though common, will beſt help you to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive of it, as indeed it is, to be inconcei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vable. Suppoſe God ſhould make a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree, (which he hath not done, and never will do) that if an Angel would take a drop of water from the Sea once in a million of Years, till he had quite emptied it; that then the miſery of the wicked ſhould have a period, when the Sea is thus quite emptied, ſo that there remaineth not one drop of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter there more: this would be an inconcei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vable term of time; and yet this would be nothing unto Eternity. Yea, if we ſhould add to the drops of water in the Sea, the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerable piles of graſs in fields, the ſmall duſt of the Earth, the particular ſands on the Sea-ſhore, the atoms or motes in the Sun, the ſmall leaves of every tree, the hairs on Men and Women's heads, and the Stars in the ſpacious Firmament; that an Angel ſhould take but one of theſe away once in a
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:105047:15"/> milion of Years, and when they are all gone with every drop of water in the Sea, and in all Rivers, that then the damned ſhould be releaſed, and be delivered from their miſeries; this would be a much more inconceivable term of time, and yet all would be nothing unto Eternity. Nay fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Suppoſe the condition of their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge from thoſe fearful miſeries they groan under were ſtraitned thus, that when an Angel had thus emptied all the Sea and every River, and carried away or removed every pile of graſs in the field, all the duſt in the Earth, the ſand on the Sea-ſhore, the atoms in the Sun, the ſmal leaves of every tree or flower, the hairs of Men and Women's heads, and all the Stars of the Firmament, by taking away only one once in a million of Years; that then at the expiration of this term of time, only one of the damned ſhould be redeemed and releaſed from their dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful miſeries and ſorrows; and ſo allow them all one after another ſucceſſively the ſame priviledg, as ſoon as the Angel had performed this condition particularly for
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:105047:16"/> each of them: This would be an inconcei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vable term of time; and yet all would be delivered at laſt, Hell would be emptied of all its inhabitants at laſt: but now, when all this ſpace of time is over and gone, Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity is no nearer ending, than it was at the very beginning of the Saints entrance into Heaven, or the wickeds entrance into Hell. When all theſe Years are paſt and expired, the Sints have as many more; yea, ten thouſand times as many more to rejoyce and triumph in. And the wicked have as many more; yea, ten thouſand times as many more to weep, and howl, and to be miſerable in. Oh, <hi>Eternity!</hi> who can conceive the length thereof? Finite Creatures cannot compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend it: when you think the utmoſt you can, Eternity runs quite beyond your thoughts, and much more beyond your ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt expreſſions. Oh! this comforts the Saints to purpoſe in the Triumphant world, that their happineſs is everlaſting, and will never, never end, expire, or have a period: And this makes helliſh inhabitants roar to purpoſe, and ſills them with horror, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:105047:16"/> confuſion and amazement, that their miſery will be everlaſting, even to the utmoſt bounds of Eternity, and never never end, expire, or have a period.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <p>3. We come to make application of this Truth, That the unſeen things of the other world are eternal. Which will be
<list>
                     <item>1. By way of Inference.</item>
                     <item>2. By way of Examination.</item>
                     <item>3. By way of Dehortation, and Caution.</item>
                     <item>4. By way of Exhortation.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <p>1. To ſpeak by way of Inference, and ſo many things may be drawn from this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine for our inſtruction: As,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Our concerns of time are certainly, but trifles and inconſiderable to unſeen things. Alas! what is time to Eternity? and what is 30, or 60, or a 100 Years, the common utmoſt bounds of our abode here, unto Eternity? 'tis but a flaſh, a vapour or a dream. Oh! whether we are miſerable or felicitous in this world, is nothing in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon of happineſs or miſery in the other.
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:105047:17"/> Mens utmoſt and longeſt day of happineſs here will be quickly at an end; and Mens utmoſt and longeſt day of miſery here will very ſpeedily expire: but Eternity, into which all muſt lanch, will never end. What a bubble is all ſublunary glory, and what a vanity is all ſublunary ignominy and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace, to the more weighty unſeen concerns that are before us? what are tranſient, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, periſhing Riches and wealth, and what is a ſhort ſeaſon of poverty or want, to the Riches of Heaven, or the neceſſities of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digent Souls in Eternity? Alas! Men put too high a price and value on Creature<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contents, and are dolefully too proud of their earthly felicity; and too much diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented with their temporal afflictions and miſeries: All concerns here, whether con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenting or not contenting, are but things that are not. And therefore the Apoſtle tells us, <hi>It remains, that both they that have wives be as though they had none, and they that weep, as though they wept not; and they that rejoyce, as though they rejoyced not; and they that buy, as though they poſſeſſed not; and they
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:105047:17"/> that uſe the world, as not abuſing it, for the faſhion of this worldpaſſeth away,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.29, 30, 31. Sorrow and joy here, if rightly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered with Eternity, are nothing, or at leaſt much leſs matters than mortals eſteem them; even the greateſt felicity and infelicity upon the borders of time are poor inconſiderable things, if ſeriouſly weighed and compar'd with the Unſeen things of the other world, which are eternal.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Of what conſequence and weighty import is the well or ill improvement of time here? as time is ſpent here, ſo will be our eternal portion. As our daies, hours and Years are husbanded here, will be our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward for ever and for ever. Heaven or Hell attend us, the enjoyments whereof are ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting, according as we ſow here. As hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs or miſery in this world is light, tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vial and inconſiderable to the weighty un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeen things that are before us: ſo our judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of them is of eternal conſequence. Time well ſpent, though it be but a ſhort ſeaſon, will be our happy and everlaſting advantage; and time ill ſpent, though it be very ſhort, will be our detriment and dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage.
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:105047:18"/> Here the Seed of that harveſt of felici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty or miſery that all reap in the other world is ſown: You have no more time or opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity to provide for your eternal peace, but your preſent day of mercy and grace. And the neglect or abuſe of your preſent tranſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory daies or hours will everlaſtingly undo you. Oh! 'tis not to no purpoſe that you are called upon to redeem your time, and prize every inch of the Day of grace that is before you, and to work whilſt 'tis called (to day,) and not to harden your hearts whilſt opportunity laſteth: Alas! an eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of joy or ſorrow and miſery depends on it. He that allures you to trifle away your precious time, allures you to make ſhipwrack of eternal mercies, and to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture on eternal wrath, diſtreſs and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexity. And how dreadful ſhould tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptations to ſuch folly and madneſs be to us?</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Sin is no light matter, for 'tis the ſeed of unſeen ſorrow in the other world, which is eternal: 'tis the ſeed of Hell, and the furious rebuke of the infinitely terrible and dreadful God for ever and for ever. This is little conſidered by the generality, who
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:105047:18"/> wallow in it like ſwine as in their element<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> little do they think, or at leaſt they have no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſtrong convictions, that it prepares never ending exquiſite and perfect miſery for them. Materially ſome ſins are final matters<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as <hi>Adam</hi>'s eating the forbidden-fruit, or the ſpeaking of a vain word, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but formally<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and in its curſed wages, nothing is a greater evill. If ſinners did but ſee the doleful<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> fruit that iniquity bears, they would dread and abhor it in publick and in private, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> they do extremity of miſery, or Hell it ſelf<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Oh! how injurious is that which moſt take to be their profit and advantage? what doth the world more hurt finally than ſin? what brings the rational Creature under God's eternal diſpleaſure, but iniquity? what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever content at preſent any have in ſin or wickedneſs, be ſure they will have none in the everlaſting pernicious and curſed conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quents of it: they will not make light of it when it hath brought them under the miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, that are the portion of the damned for ever.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. What a dreadful evill is unbelief<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Alas! this is the cauſe of all other ſins: and
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:105047:19"/> Mens dreadful making light of the weighty <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nſeen things that are before them. Men <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ear that the happineſs and miſery of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ther world is eternal; and that here we ſow <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>or our portion there: but they do not be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ieve it, or but ſuperficially believe it; that is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he reaſon why Heaven is neglected, and not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ecured, and why its eternal mercies and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oyes are ſlighted; and that is the reaſon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hy Hell and its everlaſting miſeries and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>orrows are no more induſtriouſly ſhunned, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd that ſin the ſeed thereof is no more ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>orred and lothed. Alas! who could for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hort periſhing concerns ſlight theſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conceivably weighty concerns of eternity, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hat did to purpoſe believe their certainty, or had through convincing apprehenſions of their verity? Oh! unbelief is a more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon malady than Mens profeſſion intimates; moſt are unbelievers, and the faith of thoſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hat do ſincerely believe hath ſome unbelief mix'd with it; otherwiſe unſeen things would have more influence upon them. The great reaſon, why Believers themſelves are not more the world's wonders in their ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnal and remarkable ſelf-denyal, crucifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xion
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:105047:19"/> &amp; eſtrangedneſs to the vanities of time<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> is becauſe their faith is but imperfect and infirm. Alas! the weightineſs of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns of Heaven and Hell would certainly work the greateſt contempt in us of the things here below; if we were as ſenſible of it, as ere long we ſhall be. Oh! unbelie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> is that which undoth the World, keeping them from knowing and firmly purſuing the things of their eternal peace.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. What an unſpeakable price is <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s Love and Blood? what a ſingular mercy and rich advantage to ſinners is the Redem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption that <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath wrought for us? The mercies of eternity would never have been our portion, had it not been for <hi>Chriſt;</hi> and eternal miſery perdition and deſtruction would certainly have been our portion, had it not been for <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s appearing for our ſalvation and deliverance. After a few daies ſpent upon the borders of time, we ſhould all have been the fire-brands of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quenchable fire, and the veſſels of God's fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious rebukes to eternity without remedy, had it not been for <hi>Chriſt.</hi> But <hi>Chriſt</hi> being incarnated, and having ſatisfied juſtice, and
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:105047:20"/> purchaſed a Goſpel-Covenant, we are now <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>apable of eſcaping everlaſting ſorrow and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>erplexity, and of triumphing eternally <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> God's Love and Mercy. And what a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ich and glorious priviledg is this? how <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>appy are we if we knew, and had wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>om to lay hold on the things of our peace <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd comfort? We may be happy for ever, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hrough <hi>Chriſt,</hi> if we will look about us. Eternal life through <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s Blood is ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ainable, if we are not wanting to our ſelves: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd that everlaſting wrath, which we have deſerved will never be our portion, if we do but ark our ſelves in <hi>Chriſt.</hi> Oh! <hi>Chriſt</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s the greateſt price that ever was put into <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he hands of mortals; and they are the wiſeſt Men that know his worth, and prize him <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ccordingly: And they are fools and mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men that lightly eſteem and neglect him.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. The Word and Ordinances of the Goſpel are likewiſe an ineſtimable price in our hands: for theſe help us to acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance with, and ſecurity about theſe unſeen concerns. Alas! notwithſtanding all that <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath done for us, if we had not the <hi>Word</hi> among us, we ſhould eternally without
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:105047:20"/> queſtion periſh and be undone. How ſhould we ever know the way to Heaven, or an eſcape from the wrath to come with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out this? how eaſily would Hell beguile the beſt of us, &amp; cauſe us to make ſhipwrack of our eternal hopes, and ſow the ſeed of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal miſery, had it not been for this? Many poor <hi>Heathens</hi> are therefore in a lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table condition, that have nothing but the dim light of Nature to help them in this weighty affair: though they know, or have have ſome imperfect or ſuperficial convi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of another life in the other world, where it ſhall go well with the Good, and ill with the Bad; yet they do not know the way to true Happineſs. The Book of Nature preacheth not <hi>Chriſt</hi> or his Redeeming Love to ſinners: multitudes are in darkneſs and blindneſs in compariſon of thoſe that are priviledged with the Scripture. Little do many that are only under the Tutorage of the Light of Nature, know of their duty, or of their ſin; and what wonder is it then that they walk not in the way of Life, or forſake not the way of eternal death? And thoſe that now enjoy the Word and Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:105047:21"/> of the Goſpel, if they ſhould be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived of them, will be in no ſmall danger of loſing their eternal hopes: In a little time they may forget thoſe precious truths they are acquainted with; or at leaſt the conſtant preaching of temptations, and the Spirit of ſeduction may in time wear off the impreſſion the Word had formerly made upon them. Experience tells us, that the frequent preſſing of the ſame truths is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to their effectual influence upon the hearts of mortals, and to the prevention of the frauds and cheats of their Spiritual enemies: Without the Word and Ordinances of <hi>Chriſt</hi> Men will not ſow for eternal Life; yea, they will certainly ſow the ſeed of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal death. And what a mercy doth this beſpeak the Word and Ordinances to be? And what enemies are they to a people that deprive them of theſe mercies, conſidering the weightineſs of eternal concerns that are before us?</p>
                  <p n="7">7. They are unworthy of unſeen mercies that ſlothfully careleſly and indifferently proſecute them: They bid too low a price for theſe ſtupendious Bleſſings, and judge
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:105047:21"/> themſelves unfit to enjoy them, that faintly or lukewarmly mind them. How righteouſly will they miſs of everlaſting Triumphs, that think it much all the daies of their vanity here to ſweat and labour to make them ſure? And how righteouſly will they be the Veſſels of eternal miſery, that think not ſalvation from it worth their utmoſt endeavours du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring their ſhort abode here? Alas! that there ſhould be any ſo diſmally unreaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable thus to undervalue Everlaſting con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns; and yet what more common, gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral or epidemical malady in the world? though theſe are the moſt weighty affair; yet they are not at all, or inconſiderably minded by the moſt. Moſt ſeek after eternal life, as if it were a matter of ſmalleſt moment: Moſt prefer the trivial concerns of time before them. Men's greateſt care and moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant endeavours are about temporal enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, what they ſhall eat, or drink, or wherewith they ſhall be clothed; or how they ſhall be Great, or felicitous or happy here; whereas Eternity is allow'd only thoſe ſcraps of time &amp; care, that the world or their earthly concerns can ſpare. <hi>Oh!</hi> very
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:105047:22"/> few live like ſtrangers here in the exerciſe of ſelf-denyal and contempt of Creature<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comforts and enjoyments; 'tis but a little flock that to purpoſe maketh it the buſineſs of their daies to work out their ſalvation, and make ſure their everlaſting peace and comfort; and how deſervedly then is ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Life entailed and confined only to a little flock? If never ending felicity be not worth the work and utmoſt diligence of a few daies and years, 'tis worth nothing: and if ſalvation, from Hell and the diſmal mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries there attending the damned for ever more be not worth conſtancy in duty, and utmoſt faithfulneſs during the little ſeaſon of mortals abode here, 'tis worth nothing.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. The Unholy and Ungodly are unmeet and unfit to dwell in Heaven: The enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments thereof are ſo much againſt their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, that they will ſoon be weary of them; they cannot endure holy work, or ſuch a holy place a little while, and much leſs for ever. None but thoſe that have Godlineſs for their element are meet for the everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing mercies of the Paradiſe of God. None elſe will delight to be houſed in that eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:105047:22"/> Dwelling. Thoſe that are enemies to holy love, and praiſe and duty to God; what ſhould they do there, where there is nothing elſe? All that dwell in God's trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phant Kingdom muſt make holineſs their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light; and this the wicked do not, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore are unmeet for theſe Eternal mercies.</p>
                  <p n="9">9. Afflictions and ſharp providences that cauſe us to mind Unſeen concerns moſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſely and effectually are happy diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. Alas! 'tis better to weep and groan diſmally for a ſmall ſeaſon, than for ever: 'tis better to be in heavineſs and diſtreſs for a ſhort moment, than to eternity: and Heaven's joy being everlaſting will certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fully make amends for all our temporal ſufferings how great ſoever: Though we ſhould lye in extremity of miſery during the age of <hi>Methuſalah;</hi> yet if all be ſanctified to our never ending comfort and triumph, we ſhall not (ere long) repent it, but call our miſeries happy miſeries, and our afflictions happy afflictions.</p>
                  <p>This was that which ſupported and cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed our Apoſtle and the reſt of his Brethren to rejoyce under all the moſt terrible pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>videnc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>es attending them in the exerciſe of
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:105047:23"/> their duty and faithfulneſs, that they worked for them a far more exceeding and eternal weight of Glory. Yea, all that are bound for Heaven are more or leſs the Sons and Daughters of ſorrow here: God eſtrangeth them from the world and its vanities by many ſharp and ſevere tryals here; and yet Eternity makes them glad of theſe whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom ſeverities, and cauſeth them to bleſs God for theſe medicinal and healthful cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections. Oh! 'tis happy for the Saints that God hedgeth up their way with thorns, that they may not ſin againſt him: 'Tis their high priviledg, that they have be times God's fatherly ſharp rebukes to preſerve them from making ſhipwrack of their eternal hopes: Alas! if they did not mourn &amp; weep dolefully here, they would be in danger of weeping and mourning much more dole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully to all eternity in Hell; and that would be dreadful indeed, and beſpeak them miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable indeed.</p>
                  <p n="10">10. How happy a change will the Pious have, and how diſmal and doleful a change will the Impious have, when Death hath done its work upon them, or when they lanch into the other world? Oh! how the
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:105047:23"/> Righteous will rejoyce, when they are ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible of the alteration of their condition for the better to the utmoſt date of eternity! And oh! how the wicked will be horribly amazed, when they are ſenſible of the altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their condition for the worſe to the utmoſt limits and bounds of eternity! When the Godly find themſelves landed in the Kingdom of their Father, where joys and triumphs, glory and inconceivable felicity attend them world without end, what a rapture of grateful exhilaration will ſeize upon them? And when the wicked find themſelves thruſt or hurled into the infer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal priſon, where ſorrow and miſery in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection muſt be their everlaſting never cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing or ending portion; what an overwhelm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and heart-ſinking flood of anguiſh horrour and dreadful amazement will ſeize upon them? Oh! how far will the Holy be from repenting of their duty and faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to God and their Souls then, whatever hardſhips or extremities they here grapled with in purſuance of them? and how cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly and dolefully will the impious and finally impenitent repent of their wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:105047:24"/> and neglects of <hi>CHRIST</hi> and their Souls then, how highly ſoever they were dignified or priviledged here by it? they will both find eternity preſenting them with ſuch weighty concerns as will beſpeak all creatures, and earthly concerns to be but trifles. The Godly will be perfectly ſeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citous for ever and for ever: and the wicked will be completely and perfectly miſerable, and eternally ſo.</p>
                  <p n="11">11. What a vain conceit is the Doctrine of merit and works of <hi>Supererogation?</hi> Some <hi>Papiſts</hi> hold, that 'tis not only poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for the Religious to merit Heaven for themſelves, but alſo for others: but alas! who can believe it, that doth ſoberly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the weightines of thoſe mercies they ſay they merit? what proportion is there between their work and their wages? what is a few Years holineſs or ſervice to God to an eternity of Mercy and Glory? Surely 'tis amazing Grace that doth privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg the moſt righteous, holy and pious with Heaven's Everlaſting Bleſſings. 'Tis Infinite Mercy that doth reward the ſhort, finite and tranſitory performances and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:105047:24"/> of the Religious with never end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing conſolation and felicity, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.8, 9. The worth of <hi>Chriſt</hi> may indeed hence be gathered, who really did merit theſe eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Mercies for us, and upon the account of whom the Saints are heirs of this ſtupen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious Reward: But alas! the Saints them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves are but finite Creatures, and their ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice and duty but finite; and between fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niteneſs and infiniteneſs there is no propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Oh! the beſt of Men cannot merit the joyes of Heaven, but muſt be beholden to an intereſt in amazing Grace for a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticipation of them, becauſe they are eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal. Perſons of this perſwaſion, that their works are meritorious of the inconceivably glorious Bleſſings of Eternity, do over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>value themſelves and duties, and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>value the Saints Triumphant and Eternal Bleſſings.</p>
                  <p n="12">12. God is the beſt Maſter, and the worſt enemy: God's love is moſt valuable, and his fury and frowns moſt diſmal. This is he that can priviledg us with never end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing joy, or reward us with never ending miſery. None can ſo well requite their
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:105047:25"/> ſervants, as God can and will; and none can ſo dreadfully avenge themſelves on their enemies, as God can and will. In God's favour there is eternal life, and in his wrath there is nothing but eternal death. Happy are the people that have GOD for their God and Friend, for they ſhall be felicitous world without end: and cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed are the people that have GOD for their righteous adverſary; for they will be miſerable world without end. This is he that can ſave or deſtroy for ever, and will diſpoſe of us Body and Soul to eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity. Oh! there is none whoſe love can thus reward us; and there is none whoſe hatred can thus injure us, as <hi>Jehovah</hi>'s will.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>So much by way of inference from the Doctrine.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <p>2. To ſpeak by way of Examination: Do you enquire whether you are bound for E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Life, or Eternal Death? Will the Unſeen things of Heaven or Hell be your never ending portion? have you ſow'd for everlaſting joy or ſorrow? for eternal com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort or diſcomfort? 'Tis certain you muſt
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:105047:25"/> have your portion of Unſeen things, which you hear are eternal: you are all marching toward an everlaſting eſtate, and you do here ſow the ſeed of an harveſt of never end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and never ſading happineſs or miſery: And are you not then concerned to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der what is like to be your portion? Oh! Sirs, enquire whether you are the heirs of happineſs or miſery, which ſhall laſt for ever. Conſider whether you are like to triumph, or weep and howl to an endleſs eternity: Conſider whether God will be your Friend, or your enemy for ever. Really this is no light or contemptible af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fair; 'tis infinitely more conſiderable than all concerns here below. Be careful there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to ſearch impartially for ſatisfaction in this. The uncertainty of your lives, and the weightineſs of this concern, ſhould prompt you to faithfulneſs, diligence and ſpeed in this enquiry. And indeed what greater concern have you to mind? what trifles, and how trivial are all concerns here to this? alas! 'tis nothing conſiderable whether you are high or low, rich or poor, in ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity or proſperity here in compariſon of
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:105047:26"/> what ſhall be your eternal portion. You are inexpreſſibly fooliſh and mad in mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any thing here in the neglect of this weighty concern.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Enquire after theſe things following, if you would be ſatisfied, and not deceived in this Affair.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. What have you made your bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſineſs? or what hath been the main bent and aim of your Souls during the daies of your vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty here? what is it that all your Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takings and endeavours are ſubordinate to? Is it Heaven, the enjoyment of God in Glory; or the contents of time? can you ſay, that you are ſeekers for Glory and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality in the main courſe of our lives, yea, or no? The generality mind Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concerns, or what will or ſhall become of them for ever only by the by; whilſt world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly or periſhing concerns are moſt minded and chiefly purſued. Oh! enquire whether this be not your caſe.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Are you arrived beyond the attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of hypocrites in Grace and Holineſs? can you ſay that you are got beyond the
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:105047:26"/> bounds of common Grace and Sanctifica<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion? have you not merely a common re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pentance, a common Faith, and a common love to God, and fear of him, and a common obedience to him? The generality among us are deceived in this weighty affair by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Grace, which cauſeth them to think they are the Veſſels and Heirs of Heaven, when they are not.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. What delight have you in Holineſs and duty to God? is it your meat and drink? is it your Element? could you be content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with or take pleaſure in an eternal Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of holy love, duty and praiſe to the Infinite <hi>Jehovah?</hi> Alas! what ſhould you do for ever in Glory, if you delight not in theſe exerciſes, which will be the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal work of Saints in the Kingdom of their Father? Heaven will be no Heaven to you, whilſt obedience to God and Spiritual en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyments are your burden, and not your recreation and complacency. By this therefore do you enquire whether you are bound for Heaven and eternal Life; yea, or no.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:105047:27"/>
                  <p>3. We come to ſpeak ſomething by way <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>f Dehortation. And is it ſo, that Unſeen <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hings are eternal? then</p>
                  <div n="1" type="subsection">
                     <p>1. Take heed of ſowing the ſeed of ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ow, grief or miſery in the other world; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>or you hear it will be eternal. Oh! take <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>eed at any rate of plunging your ſelves un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the unſeen wrath, fury and vengeance of the <hi>Great Jehovah;</hi> for you ſee it will be of everlaſting duration. You read of ſome that treaſure up for themſelves wrath againſt the day of wrath, and revelation of the Righteous Judgment of God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.5. Oh! let not this be the caſe of any of you. Yea, the generality of Men, and moſt Profeſſours do walk in the broad way leading to everlaſting deſtruction, <hi>Matth.</hi> 7.13. do you take heed that you be not of their number. And for that end take heed of hypocriſy: for the hypocrites in heart heap up wrath, <hi>Job</hi> 36.13. Watch alſo againſt every ſin; for the wages or fruit of it is eternal death, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.23. Get ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance with the things of your eternal peace; for you find God himſelf complain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſometimes that for want of knowledg
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:105047:27"/> his people periſh, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 4.6. Be careful to be delivered from an evill heart of unbelief for he that believeth not w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap> be damned <hi>Mark</hi> 16.16. Die not in impe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>cy; for thoſe that repent not will certa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap> be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed, <hi>Luke</hi> 13.3. Live not af<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>er the fleſh; for he that liveth after the fleſh muſt die, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8,13. Take heed of pride; for this goeth before deſtruction, <hi>Prov.</hi> 16.18. Abhor unmercifulneſs and cruelty; for he ſhall have judgment without mercy, that ſheweth no mercy, <hi>James</hi> 2.13. Eſpecially neglect not the relief of <hi>Chriſt</hi> in his indigent Members; for you ſee this is given as the reaſon of that dreadful ſentence, that will paſs on the veſſels of perdition at the laſt day, <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.41, 42. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And laſtly dread diſ-obedience to the Goſpel of <hi>Chriſt;</hi> for <hi>Chriſt</hi> will come (ere long) to take everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vengeance on thoſe that obey not his Goſpel, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 18. Oh Sirs, you are in fearful danger; be not in inſenſible of it, and do not further it. Live not in peril of eternal damnation: do not make ſure ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting burnings for your ſelves: if you would not groan for ever under inſuppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:105047:28"/> miſeries, take heed of being heirs of them. 'Tis here that ſinners prepare for their never ending horror in the other world; be not you guilty of this folly and madneſs.</p>
                     <p>And for that end conſider,</p>
                     <p n="1">1. That moſt do ſow for Hell and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, and accordingly will reap the doleful harveſt thereof to all eternity; moſt are in the broad way leading to the cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of everlaſting death; yea, multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes of thoſe, that to others ſeem bound for Heaven, are certainly bound for per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition world without end. Oh! you have need to look about you, conſidering what abundance miſcarry in this affair; and eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially what abundance that ſeem to bid fair for Heaven, do yet eternally loſe their Souls. There are many that pray and faſt, and in ſome ſort mourn for and repent of their ſins, and live in the exerciſe of much holy duty; that yet remain in the gall of bitterneſs, and at length groan under the inſupportable wrath of God for evermore. 'Tis but a very little flock, even among Profeſſours, that effectually take heed of
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:105047:28"/> the ſeed of Hell, and eternal damnation. Therefore you are fearfully concerned to look about you.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. You have a wicked nature within you addicted to this Soul-undoing courſe. The hearts of Men and Women are deſperately evill: The ſeed of Hell is in your breaſts already. 'Tis very difficult for you to eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cape the ſnares and entanglements of ſin &amp; death through the doleful propenſity of your Souls to comply with them: 'Tis up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this account that the Righteous are ſcarcely ſaved; and that the beſt of Saints have ſo much ado to avoid the wrath to come. If you are not very watchful, the evill heart within you will be your eternal perdition without fail. The law in your members will certainly captivate you to your everlaſting doleful prejudice. Oh! how natural is pride, fleſh-pleaſing and worldlineſs to ſinful Man, which are the ſeed of Helliſh miſery? And how doth carnal intereſt covertly, ſecretly and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſibly ſway the Souls of multitudes to their utter deſtruction? you are in doleful peril of ſowing for eternal miſery. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:105047:29"/> you are concerned to take heed.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. Sorrow, and much leſs eternal ſorrow in the other world, is not deſirable; 'tis much leſs deſirable unſpeakably than a har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt of miſery, and utmoſt extremities and calamities here: Yea, 'tis moſt abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent as the greateſt evill. Alas! what is more dreadful to mortals than ſevere pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments? and what greater ſeverity of miſery is there, than what is the curſed fruit of ſin in the eternal <hi>Ocean?</hi> The damneds roarings and heart-ſinking lamentation in Hell do evidence that their portion there is moſt diſmal. The ſtouteſt heart will tremble (as the ſinners in <hi>Sion</hi> are ſaid to do) when they are to purpoſe ſenſible what they adventure on by ſin in the other world; and cry, <hi>Who among us ſhall dwell with devouring fire? who among us ſhall dwell with everlaſting burnings? Iſa.</hi> 33.14. De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liberately none would chooſe deſtruction, and much leſs everlaſting deſtruction. Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners know not what they do, when they treaſure up wrath for their Souls in the Unſeen world: They little dream that they ſtore up ſuch fearful and dreadful ſorrows,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:105047:29"/> as they muſt reap when they have left the borders of time. Oh! Sirs, 'tis extremity of miſery, or perfection of calamity, that you are now cautioned againſt. 'Tis that infelicity, which will be the moſt eminent diſplay of God's hotteſt fury and indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and what can be imagined to be more dreadful? Be careful therefore at any rate to flie from the wrath to come, and not to make light of it, conſidering how diſmal it is, and not deſirable.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. You have a better price in your hand; you may ſow for Heaven, and the Bleſſings of God's Paradiſe. You may lay a foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation for comfort, peace and glorious joy, inſtead of miſery and diſmal ſorrow in the other world, if you will look about you: working out your Salvation is not impoſſible. Oh! you may live with God to your triumphant conſolation, if not wanting to your ſelves. And ſhould ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Creatures neglect this Prize, and chooſe aſtoniſhing horrour? Is Happineſs contemptible, and miſery eligible and to be preferr'd before it? How dolefully mad are the wicked and hypocrites in ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glecting
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:105047:30"/> the Bleſſings, and ſowing for the curſes and calamities of the other world? God forbid, that any of you ſhould be guilty of this folly and madneſs. Oh! Sirs, remember Life and Immortality is brought to light through the Goſpel, and Heaven's Mercies and amazing enjoyments are obtainable by ſinful duſt and worms. You are capable of becoming the Heirs of the matchleſs and unſpeakable triumphs of the Kingdom of God. And can you imagin that you ſhall not dolefully lament the loſs of this Price, if you loſe it, and ſow for Hell, and its inexpreſſible miſeries?</p>
                     <p n="5">5. Conſider the weight of Unſeen things from this conſideration in the Doctrine, that they are eternal: And let that prompt you to take heed of ſowing for ſorrow in the other world. Alas! what ſad preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice do you adventure Body and Soul up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by ſuch a doleful ſeedneſs? If miſery in perfection for a ſeaſon were tolerable; yet ſurely eternal exquiſite miſery, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſant weeping and wailing for ever, will be intolerable: and believe it, if you look not about you, you will have an eternity
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:105047:30"/> of time horribly to lament your ſtupendious and amazing folly. Oh! you that are im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patient and reſtleſs under God's light af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction for a ſeaſon here, and that cannot quietly bear the pain of the head-ach, Gout, or Stone for a little time; how will you be able to endure the utmoſt revelation of God's moſt terrible indignation in Hell? Oh! to be howling incredibly a whole e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity without intermiſſion, and without ending, how horrible and dreadful is it? If you do not therefore like eternal burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and miſery, take heed of ſowing the ſeed of it, and become not the heirs thereof.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="subsection">
                     <p>2. Take heed that the things of time do not joſtle out your care of Unſeen things. Let not this world's concerns cauſe you to neglect or be mindleſs of the Unſeen world's concerns. This is the folly that the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality are guilty of: They prefer temporal riches before eternal, and momentany plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures before everlaſting. Let not this be the caſe of any of you. Oh! learn to look on all things here as vanity and nothing in compariſon of the weighty affairs of
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:105047:31"/> Heaven and Hell. Remember you ſhall be here but a little while, and all enjoyments here will be of uſe to you but for a very ſhort ſeaſon; take heed that you be not gulled, as the <hi>Rich man</hi> in the Goſpel, by a fancied ſelicity in Creature-contents, <hi>Luke</hi> 12.19, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Alas! what is it that keeps perſons from the power of Religion, but things that are ſeen? what coſeneth the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerality out of their everlaſting hope, but t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap> things of time? They cannot live in ſelf-den<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> or renunciation of viſible com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts; that is the reaſon why eternal Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies are indiffe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>ly and lukewarly pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued: Things that are ſeen have their hearts, that is the reaſon why Heaven and Eternal life is neglected. Oh! Sirs, take heed of this folly in doting upon things that are but temporal. Look upon them as they are, trample them under your ſeet in compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the ſtupendiouſly more weighty con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns of Eternity. Live like ſtrangers here with weaned affections from all terrene en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyments.</p>
                     <p>'Tis certain you will never ſow for Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven elſe, you will never become the heirs
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:105047:31"/> of everlaſting Bleſſings; unleſs you are dead to the world and fleſhly delights. All the portion of comfort and peace you ſhall ever have will be only in this world, unleſs you diſengage your Souls from the vanities of time. What ever profeſſion you make, or how ever any may flatter you, you ſhall never win <hi>CHRIST</hi> or Eternal Life, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs you can looke upon all things here as droſs or dung in compariſon of Unſeen things, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.8.</p>
                     <p>And certain it is, that the ſtronger your Faith is, the more you will deſpiſe, and the leſs you will be impeded in your Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian courſe by, concerns here. The be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving Soul will certainly be a ſelf-deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Soul. Can you believingly view the Glorious and weighty enjoyments of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and Hell, and not have undervaluing thoughts and conceits of temporal enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments? Oh 'tis an argument that you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>believers, whilſt ordinarily you permit earthly contents to rule and ſway you. Alas! what trifles are all our ſublu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>y af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, to thoſe that are arrived to the ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Souls? and what fools do they ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:105047:32"/> mortals in ſetting ſuch an eſtimation on them as they do? And if your Faith were ſtrong, it would be equivalent to ſenſe, and have the ſame impreſſion on you. Oh! if you would be accounted Believers, and conſequently <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> you muſt ſlight temporal concerns, and let Heaven have chiefly your heart and affection.</p>
                     <p>Remember alſo the cloud of Witneſſes that have gone before you, that have lived like ſtrangers here, and looked upon all the contents of this life as vanity and emptineſs, and trampled viſible enjoyments under their feet in purſuance of the more glorious hope before t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>n. Alas! there would have been no <hi>Martyrs</hi> in the world, if there had not been ſelf-denying Men and Women abroad. Yea, there is not a perſon got to Glory, but what was mortiſied to the World and the Fleſh: All that ever entred GOD's eternal Kingdom, did march through the narrow gate of cruciſixion to the vanities here be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low. And as they were accounted fools and mad-Men by the worldly Wiſe; ſo muſt we expect to be cenſured, if ever we would ſow for everlaſting Mercies.</p>
                     <pb n="59" facs="tcp:105047:32"/>
                     <p>Add to this, that this is as plain a duty, as any the Scripture preſſeth, and its ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity is likewiſe as clear; they are ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers to the Scripture, that are ſtangers to this neceſſary duty. 'Tis a wonder that any, that call themſelves <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> can over-look ſo plain a caution as this is. They are moſt palpably blinded by the god of this world, that enjoy the written Word, and are not convinced that they muſt live like ſtrangers here.</p>
                     <p>So, how deeply will you repent it, if your reſpect to Creatureconcerns cauſe you to loſe Eternal Mercies? When Eternity hath opened your eyes to ſee your loſs, and for what inconſiderable things you have loſt everlaſting joy and triumphs, you will dole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully lament it: Then you will know that Creature felicity was but a bubble, and that the higheſt and moſt valuable enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments here were but a ſhadow or dream to thoſe more ſubſtantial and neverfading con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents you have made ſhipwrack of. And you cannot now imagine how Conſcience will then afflict you for ſuch groſs folly and madneſs: eſpecially when it appears that
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:105047:33"/> your loſs of Heaven is irrecoverable, and you muſt for ever be ſhut out of the Habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Bleſſed: And eſpecially when you find that your temporal felicity is your eternal bane, and for your ſhort en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment of theſe fading comforts you muſt be miſerable, and roar under God's inſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portable wrath for ever more. The <hi>Rich man</hi> in the Goſpel that here enjoyed his good things to full content, when he had loſt Heaven and his Soul, and was torment<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in theſe flames that were unquenchable, could not chuſe but dolefully repent of his madneſs in taking up with, and doting up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſuch vanities as his portion. Yea, doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs this doth fill Hell with roaring, to think for what trifles they loſt Eternal Life, and purchaſed to themſelves eternal death. Take heed therefore of this deſperate mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. Prefer not in your practical judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments or eſtimation temporal concerns, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore eternal: and ſuffer not the things of time, to cauſe you to neglect, or be cold or indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent in your purſuit after Everlaſting Mercies: rather live like ſtrangers here, and trample under your feet all earthly
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:105047:33"/> enjoyments; that you may be heirs of God's eternal Kingdom, and not be puniſhed e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſtingly from his preſence, and the glory of his power.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="subsection">
                     <p>3. You that are Godly, take heed of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing diſcontented or diſcouraged with the portion of evill things here attending you, conſidering that your reward is eternal. Be not offended with the ſorrows or miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries way-laying you in your paſſage to Glory, conſidering the weightineſs of the Prize before you, that will make amends for all. This was the great encouragement the Apoſtles had to bear all afflictions and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings patiently; even becauſe their light afflictions, which were but for a moment, did work for them a far more exceeding and eternal weight of Glory. Oh! think it not much to groan a few daies or years, that you may eternally rejoyce; be content to weep for a ſeaſon, that you may triumph for ever: Yea, think it no marvel, if a Prize ſo glorious and weighty, as Everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Life, be attended with difficulties, and coſt you ſome ſharp, though very ſhort, afflictions, Alas! what is worth your toil
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:105047:34"/> and utmoſt ſuffering here, if Heaven and its never fading conſolations are not? and what will uphold, ſupport and keep you from ſinking under the preſſures and affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting ſorrows of this life, if the eternal weight of Glory, which you have or ſhould have in your eye, will not? Nay, will you not judge your ſelves unworthy of this Glorious Prize, whilſt you cannot patient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bear ſmall affliction in purſuance of it? The Mariner and worlding will reſolutely paſs through many a diſmal and perillous ſtorme for the poor prize of temporal riches, which they may loſe as ſoon as they enjoy; and they will ſuffer much contented<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in order to the obtainment of them: And ſhould not <hi>Chriſtians</hi> much more willingly, cheerfully and patiently endure all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>cts in order to the enjoyment of a Prize <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>itely more weighty? What ſhould not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> hope of Everlaſting Life be encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>ough to undergo and adventure on? <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> (you find) in all Ages could <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> rejoyce under utmoſt ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> of Eternal Life; and why <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>? Oh! you that are <hi>Chriſtians,</hi>
                        <pb n="63" facs="tcp:105047:34"/> learn of the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> learn of the <hi>Martyr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi> and Saints in all Ages patiently to bear th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> croſſes of this life, which are but tempo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ral; and to glory and triumph in ſuffering<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> for <hi>CHRIST,</hi> conſidering the end o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> them, which is Eternal Life.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <p>4. We come to ſpeak ſomething by way of Exhortation. And is it ſo, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Unſeen things are eternal? Then</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Be exhorted to get ſound convictions and believing apprehenſions of the truth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and weightineſs of theſe Unſeen things. See that your judgment be fully ſatisfied about the verity, and that you are to purpoſe ſenſible of the Unſpeakable ponderouſneſs of theſe great concerns. Alas! there are but very few that do really believe that an eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of ſorrow or joy will be their portion in the other world: And there are but few that in any tolerable meaſure are ſenſible; of the importance or conſequence of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity. Theſe things would otherwiſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence their hearts and lives, and be more viſible in all their carriage and deportment. How could they careleſly purſue theſe great concerns, if they had ſound and convincing
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:105047:35"/> apprehenſions of their truth and weighti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eſs? how could they chooſe but live like <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>trangers here, and in the contempt of all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>errene enjoments in compariſon of theſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hings, if they did indeed look for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>elation of them? Could Men endure to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>pend their time for trifles, or vaniſhing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd fading contents, that knew that ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aſting life or death would be their portion (ere long) according to their deportment <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ere? ſurely no. Oh! time would be more precious, and the word and ordinances of the Goſpel would be more precious, and better husbanded, if theſe things were ſoundly believed and to purpoſe conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. Be careful therefore to get your Faith in theſe affairs ſtrengthned; labour to be ſoundly convinced, that you ſhall be in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven or Hell for ever; and be ſure to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand and be ſenſible of the weightineſs of theſe things. This is the foundation of all Religion and practical Godlineſs, You'l never to purpoſe work out your ſalvation, or lay hold on Eternal Life, without this: therefore ſee to it.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Be exhorted to lament your hitherto
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:105047:35"/> ſlight care &amp; doleful lukewarmneſs in theſe weighty affairs. Lament your heartleſs pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuit after Eternal Life, and your lifeleſs en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours to eſcape eternal death. Lament your miſpent time, which might have been improved for your everlaſting comfort. Mourn over eſpecially your miſimproved <hi>Sabboths,</hi> and golden opportunities and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages for never ending felicity, which you have been fruitleſs or unprofitable un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. Oh! let your ſad neglects of the things of your eternal peace be your ſhame, &amp; pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent confuſion, and heart-afflicting grief. Alas! what have you more reaſon to lament, than your regardleſneſs of eternity? wherein did you ever ſhew greater folly or madneſs, than in your ſlighting this weighty concern? Oh! what a mercy is it that you are not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to lament with deſperation by the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincing light of eternity, what now you are called upon to lament in a day of Grace be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hope is gone? You do not know how ſoon you may be compelled to mourn over your folly in this affair in Hell, if you mourn not over it now in order to your future ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage and comfort. And alas! who is there
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:105047:36"/> that hath not cauſe enough to be covered with confuſion for their mindleſneſs of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity in the daies of their preſent vanity; &amp; the inconſiderable preparation they have made for their comfort in that <hi>Ocean?</hi> We have too much reaſon to be aſhamed for our dull proſecution of theſe weighty concerns.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Be exhorted to make ſure work for Eternal Life; and to give diligence to lay hold on the everlaſting Bleſſings of the Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeen world. Oh! build firmly for your peace and triumph in that Kingdom, which will laſt for ever: ſpare no expenſe of time, ſtrength or coſt in this weighty affair. Wherever you are ſlothful, unfaithful or careleſs, ſee that utmoſt unwearied dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence and faithfulneſs be uſed here. Make this the buiſineſs of your daies to ſow for E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting joy &amp; comfort when time is gone. Yea, ſee that you have no Imployment or affair, but what is undertaken and managed in a due ſubſerviency to this weighty affair. Alas! Sirs, what greater buiſineſs have you to mind? what an infinitely glorious prize doth the Unſeen world ſet before you? and how poor and inconſiderable are all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:105047:36"/> of time to it? You ſpend your time and ſtrength for trifles, whatever you purſue, if you neglect Heaven &amp; Eternal Life. Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Kingdoms and Crowns are but ſhadows and vanity to the everlaſting ſubſtantial en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyments of the Paradiſe of GOD, which you are invited to ſecure for your Souls. 'Tis a wonder that the World ſhould have in it a rational creature, that can find himſelf em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment without reference to his comfort in the Eternal <hi>Ocean;</hi> the concerns thereof are ſo infinitely weighty above all the things of time. Oh; be not you ſo unreaſonable, do not you thus neglect your own greateſt, moſt neceſſary and moſt glorious mercies. For periſhing fading contents let not never ending and everlaſting triumphing Bleſſings be loſt and jeoparded. Seriouſly conſider the weightineſs of theſe concerns, and ſurely they will influence you to utmoſt faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs for the aſſuring of them. Everlaſting joy or ſorrow what is there here that is any thing like it? Triumphs or howlings for evermore what on Earth bears any compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon to them? If any thing here be worth your care or minding, ſurely eternity and
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:105047:37"/> its concerns are infinitely more conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, and ſhould be infinitely more influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>encing.</p>
                  <p>The Joyes of Heaven are Mercies indeed; they are the moſt inconceivable glorious Bleſſings. There's happineſs in perfection, fulneſs of joy, peace, content and comfort, without a dram of ſorrow, in glory. There God is to be enjoy'd, who is All in all. There are Rivers of pleaſure, and an <hi>Ocean</hi> of the moſt Soul-ſatisfying goodneſs. So glorious are the Bleſſings of eternity, that eye never ſaw, ear never heard, and it never entred into the heart of Man to conceive their glory, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.</p>
                  <p n="9">9. Theſe are mercies that quite ſurpaſs and exceed the very thoughts and imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of finite Men; ſo unſpeakably do they excel all contents here, and infinitely more, if you were capable to ſet your ear at Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven's door, and could hear the Souls ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſhing Songs of the glorified quire in God's Paradiſe: If there were but a hole or a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle chink, through which you might view their triumphant Robes, or if by any means you could get a glimpſe of that overflowing
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:105047:37"/> conſolation wherewith they do abound un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to eternity; no temptation will ever be ſtrong enough to make you neglect or ſlight the purſuit of their enjoyments; yea, you would certainly reach after an intereſt in them, whatever they coſt you, and would not endure a diverſion from a faithful pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution of them.</p>
                  <p>Add to this, that Eternal Life contains in it an eternal ſalvation from Helliſh mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery; if you make ſure of Heaven, you ſhall not ſip of the Lake of fire and brim-ſtone, wherein the wicked will be tormented for ever. This you are at preſent in danger of; and this you will eſcape if you become the Heirs of eternal Bleſſings. And what a rich Price is this, which yet Infinite Mercy en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſteth you with? How would the damned in Hell prize and improve it, now they have taſted helliſh ſorrows, if the privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg of hope of deliverance were yet before them? what would they not do or give for their redemption from thoſe miſeries? 'Tis not unlike but you have, or may have, all of you, ſome troubles, afflictions, croſſes, pains or miſeries to groan under here, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:105047:38"/> from which you would be willing to purchaſe at the deareſt rate: And is not redemption and deliverance from Hell much more deſirable and neceſſary? Oh! how will you value this mercy, when the Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal <hi>Ocean</hi> hath effectually acquainted you with the worth of it? to be ſaved from theſe ſorrows that are unſpeakable and never ending is a prize ineſtimable: therefore ſpare no diligence or endeavour in purſuit of it.</p>
                  <p>Moreover, remember you muſt and will be houſed in Heaven or Hell for ever: you will unqueſtionably have your portion in everlaſting joy or ſorrow: there is no a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voiding it, but you will be the veſſels of amazing mercy in God's triumphant King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom; or the veſſels of amazing wrath and indignation in unquenchable flames: And which of you can think of dwelling with devouring fire, or of being the fuell of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting burnings, without horrour? how ſhould the thoughts of your dreadful peril cauſe you to mend you pace in your Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian courſe; and double your diligence, watchfulneſs and faithfulneſs, that you may
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:105047:38"/> inherit eternal mercies? eſpecially if you conſider the qualitie and nature of that miſery, that otherwiſe will certainly over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelm you with the eternity of its dura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? Remember, miſery in perfection will be your inheritance for evermore, if you loſe Heaven's Mercies and Bleſſings; extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity of ſorrow you will endure world without end, if you have no part nor lot in the triumphs of God's Paradiſe. Once have the gate of Heaven ſhut againſt you, and it will be ſhut againſt you for ever: and once be plunged into the Infernal Lake where is weeping, and wailing, and gnaſhing of teeth without intermiſſion, and you will be hope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs of redemption from it forever. <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s love and blood will be inſignificant to you, and all the promiſes of the Goſpel will be in vain to you; and your day of Grace will be utterly unprofitable to you, and have an everlaſting period. And oh! Sirs, ſoberly conſider the weight of this adjunct eternal and everlaſting, and ſurely 'twill effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally render unſeen things moſt incompara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to you, and make them chiefly influen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial in heart and life. Upon ſerious conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:105047:39"/> you will find eternity weighty beyond your conceptions. Remember, it notes not only laſting joyes and ſorrows beyond the account of time inconceivably, and not only a continuance of happineſs and miſery without any intermiſſion; but alſo an everlaſting or never ceaſing perma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nency of felicity and calamity without any period or ending. When ſinners have been groaning and roaring in Hell under un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable torments as many millions of mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions of Years as there be drops of water in the Sea, piles of graſs in the field, ſmall duſt in the Earth, ſand on the Sea ſhore, hairs on Men and Women's heads in the world, and Stars in the Firmament; yet their miſeries, ſorrows, &amp; calamities are no nearer ending than at the beginning. And when the Saints have been triumphing in the Paradiſe of God as many more millions of millions of Years, yet ſtill their joyes, happineſs, and triumphs are no nearer expiring than at the firſt entrance into Glory. As long as God is juſt, holy and righteous, that is as long as God is God the damned muſt howl and roar under inexpreſſible miſeries: and
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:105047:39"/> the Glorified Saints muſt be ſwimming and rejoycing in triumphant Bleſſings. And how few to purpoſe conſider the weighti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of theſe things? If your danger were only to ſuffer God's hotteſt wrath, and loſe his ſpecial love for a million of years; yea, for a year or a month, 'twere yet ſo conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable as that you would forfeit your rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to ſlight this concern upon the account of any earthly happineſs whatever; and how much more unſpeakably fooliſh will you be to make light of this concern which is eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, not only of inexpreſſible but incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivable length of duration? Oh Sirs, pauſe more frequently on the meaning and weighti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Eternity, that the Goſpel-promiſes and threatnings of the Word may more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence you, and render temptations from worldly enjoyments and fleſhly delights to byaſs you from holineſs not only ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſleſs, but contemptible, and whatever you do, be careful to make ſure of eternal Life, and an eſcape from eternal miſery.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Be exhorted to perform every duty as for eternity. Faſt and pray, and humble your Souls for ſin as for eternal Life, and an
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:105047:40"/> eſcape from eternal death. Hear the Word, labour to profit by it, as perſons that know eternity depends upon it; love and ſerve God as for eternity. As <hi>Solomon</hi> adviſeth, <hi>Whatſoever thy hand ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ndeth to do, do it with thy might, for there is no work, n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>r device, nor knowledg, nor wiſedom in the grave whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thou goeſt, Eccleſ.</hi> 9.10. Set all the powers of your Souls on work in every duty: for in Eternity you can't amend what is amiſs, you muſt then reap the curſed fruit of your negligence, ſloth and unfaith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs in duty; but you will not have op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity or ability to reform your miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carriages in order to one dram of comfort or conſolation for your Souls. As <hi>Zeuxes</hi> therefore of old was uſed to draw his Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures with ſingular exacteneſs, becauſe (as he ſaid) he painted for eternity: even ſo ſhould we be induſtrious and exact in what we do, becauſe all is for eternity. Oh! ask your Souls in all your undertakings and endeavours, Is this to work for eternity? do I now improve my ſelf like a perſon ſenſible that an eternity of joy or ſorrow, happineſs or miſery depends upon my pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:105047:40"/> carriage and deportment? Shall I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flect back with heart-ſinking remorſe and regret, or with heart-raviſhing content and ſatisfaction upon my preſent work in the <hi>Ocean</hi> of eternity? Say and think of every action, what if this ſhould be my laſt? what if eternity ſhould ſwallow me preſently, and bring me to God's impartial and eternal Judgment? and accordingly with utmoſt vigour and faithfulneſs be found in your duty, and the exerciſe of your integrity in purſuit of everlaſting Bleſſings.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
